<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Notenik News</title>
  <subtitle>The latest news about the Notenik app</subtitle>
  <link href="https://notenik.app/atom.xml" type="application/atom+xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://notenik.app/" type="text/html" rel="alternate"  />
  <updated>2021-10-14T09:00:00Z</updated>
  <rights>Copyright © 2021, Herb Bowie</rights>
  <author>
	<name>Herb Bowie</name>
  </author>
  <id>https://hbowie.net/atom.xml</id>
	<entry>
	  <title>Notenik 7.4.0 - Wiki Link Enhancements</title>
	  <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.4.0-wiki-link-enhancements.html"/>
	  <id>https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/notenik-7.4.0-wiki-link-enhancements.html</id>
	  <published>2021-10-14T09:00:00Z</published>
	  <updated>2021-10-14T12:00:00Z</updated>
	  <author>
		<name>Herb Bowie</name>
		<uri>https://hbowie.net/</uri>
	  </author>
	  <summary>
		  Notenik 7.4.0 addresses some common issues that often arise when making use of  Wiki Style Links. Welcome to backlinks, automatic target note creation, and AKA entries for your Notes! 
	  </summary>
	  <content type="html">
		  <![CDATA[
		  <p>Notenik 7.4.0 addresses some common issues that often arise when making use of  <a href="https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/wiki-style-links.html">Wiki Style Links</a>. </p>
<p><strong>Issue # 1</strong>: You&apos;re writing one Note, then realize you want that Note to link to a different Note, but that different Note does not yet exist. Before 7.4.0, Notenik would allow you to create the link but then, when you clicked on it, would just give you a (not very helpful) error message. </p>
<p>The fix? When you save a Note (or reload a Note you have edited externally, using your favorite text editor), Notenik will check all of the Note&apos;s wiki style links to make sure they point to Notes that actually exist. For any that don&apos;t yet exist, Notenik will automatically create them! And the new Note will contain a handy pointer back to the Note that created it, via its wiki style link. </p>
<p>Problem solved! </p>
<p><strong>Issue # 2</strong>: You&apos;ve named a Note one way (including a verb and an object, let&apos;s say) and then want to later refer to that Note via a wiki style link. But given the context of the reference to that Note, you want to use slightly different wording in the new sentence you&apos;re constructing (calling out just the object, let&apos;s say). </p>
<p>The solution? Now you can add a special <a href="https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/also-known-as.html">AKA</a> field to a Collection, and then add one or more alternate identifiers to a Note, allowing you to then wiki link to that Note using any of the alternates you have called out. For example, even though the <a href="https://notenik.app/docs.html">Notenik Knowledge Base</a> includes a Note for this new field that is titled &quot;Also Known As,&quot; I can link to that Note using a Wiki Link of <code>[AKA]</code>, because the <code>Also Known As</code> Note contains an <code>AKA</code> entry that calls out <code>AKA</code> as an alternate identifier for that Note. </p>
<p>Pretty handy, eh? </p>
<p><strong>Issue # 3</strong>: You&apos;ve created a bunch of wiki style links that refer to various other Notes. And now you&apos;re looking at a Note in your Collection. And you can see what other Notes are linked to from this Note, but then you wonder&hellip; which Notes, if any, link to this Note? </p>
<p>The answer? <em>Backlinks!</em> By enabling the new field type called <a href="https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/back-links.html">Backlinks</a>, Notenik will automatically keep track of backlinks in your Collection, and make them available on the Display tab. </p>
<p>And so now you have automatic bidirectional linking of Notes within a Collection: write one link to go from one Note to another, and you can then automatically traverse your wiki style links in either direction. </p>
<p><strong>And One More Thing</strong>: The Notenik Knowledge Base now has a new article in the <a href="https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/putting-it-all-together.html">Putting It All Together</a> section called <a href="https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/write-a-web-book.html">Write a Web Book</a>, that gives you some pointers on how to create a web book of your own. Hope you find it useful! </p>

		  ]]>
	  </content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
	  <title>Notenik 7.3.0 - A Handful of Helpful Refinements</title>
	  <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.3.0-a-handful-of-helpful-refinements.html"/>
	  <id>https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/notenik-7.3.0-a-handful-of-helpful-refinements.html</id>
	  <published>2021-09-30T09:00:00Z</published>
	  <updated>2021-09-30T12:00:00Z</updated>
	  <author>
		<name>Herb Bowie</name>
		<uri>https://hbowie.net/</uri>
	  </author>
	  <summary>
		  Version 7.3.0 of Notenik includes a handful of nifty changes: Improved Seq and Level Defaults for Drag and Drop; Improved Recognition of Parent Realm Folders; Parent Realm Folders Now Appear on Open Recent Menu; Streamlined New Collection process; Saving Security-Scoped Bookmarks; and Undo Provided for Note Deletions. 
	  </summary>
	  <content type="html">
		  <![CDATA[
		  <p>Version 7.3.0 of Notenik includes a handful of helpful improvements. </p>
<h5 id="improved-seq-and-level-defaults-for-drag-and-drop">Improved Seq and Level Defaults for Drag and Drop</h5>
<p>When pasting an item (such as a URL) into a List sorted by Seq, and when the drop point is between existing rows, Notenik will now do a better job of setting reasonable defaults for both Seq and Level for the new Note. </p>
<h5 id="improved-recognition-of-parent-realm-folders">Improved Recognition of Parent Realm Folders</h5>
<p>Notenik allows you to drag a folder to be opened onto its app icon in the dock. That folder can be either a Notenik Collection or a parent folder containing Notenik Collections. Before this change, if a folder contained a single text file named <code>robots.txt</code>, then that would be treated as a Note, and so the folder would be opened as a Collection. After this change, such a folder will be more productively treated as the object of an <a href="https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/open-parent-realm.html">Open Parent Realm</a> command. </p>
<h5 id="parent-realm-folders-now-appear-on-open-recent-menu">Parent Realm Folders Now Appear on Open Recent Menu</h5>
<p>After you execute the <a href="https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/open-parent-realm.html">Open Parent Realm</a> command (either explicitly via the <code>File</code> menu, or implicitly by dragging a folder onto the app icon), the Parent Realm folder will now be added to the the <code>Open Recent</code> menu, making it available to be easily reopened later. </p>
<h5 id="streamlined-new-collection-process">Streamlined New Collection process</h5>
<p>It seemed a bit confusing to have so many different options for creating a new Collection, so I&apos;ve combined them. Now there is just one <code>File</code> menu option, that says <code>New Collection&amp;hellip;</code>. This option walks you through several screens where you can pick a location, pick a name, and pick a Collection type, and then shows you the Collection Preferences screen where you can make any final adjustments to the configuration of your New Collection. </p>
<h5 id="saving-security-scoped-bookmarks">Saving Security-Scoped Bookmarks</h5>
<p>Notenik has been enhanced to try to extend the life of access permissions for Collections assigned Shortcuts, so as to reduce the number of times a user has to re-authorize access to a folder. See <a href="https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/tailor-collection-preferences.html">Tailor Collection Preferences</a> for info on assigning a Shortcut to a Collection. </p>
<h5 id="undo-provided-for-note-deletions">Undo Provided for Note Deletions</h5>
<p>If you delete a Note by mistake, then you can use the Undo function (beneath the Edit menu) to undo the deletion, with the only caveat being that any note attachments will not be restored. </p>

		  ]]>
	  </content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
	  <title>Notenik 7.2.0 - Some Nifty Enhancements</title>
	  <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.2.0-some-nifty-enhancements.html"/>
	  <id>https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/notenik-7.2.0-some-nifty-enhancements.html</id>
	  <published>2021-09-20T09:00:00Z</published>
	  <updated>2021-09-20T12:00:00Z</updated>
	  <author>
		<name>Herb Bowie</name>
		<uri>https://hbowie.net/</uri>
	  </author>
	  <summary>
		  Version 7.2.0 of Notenik includes a handful of nifty changes: the website address has been updated to point to Notenik.app; wiki links now will try to pluralize a reference, if it is not found in singular form; the Merge template Set command now allows a variable to be used as part or all of a global variable name; Markdown quote sharing corrected to respect lookup links; added a Quick Export and Open command. 
	  </summary>
	  <content type="html">
		  <![CDATA[
		  <p>Version 7.2.0 of Notenik includes a handful of nifty changes. </p>
<h4 id="new-and-improved-notenik-website">New and Improved Notenik Website</h4>
<p>The Notenik website used to reside at Notenik.net. </p>
<p>That URL will still get you there (as will Notenik.com), but the primary name for the website has now been changed to <a href="https://notenik.app/">Notenik.app</a> because &#8211; well it&apos;s all about the Notenik App! </p>
<p>More significantly, the appearance and the contents of the site have both been improved. Check it out when you get a chance! </p>
<p>And, for those of you who are interested, the Notenik site is itself generated by a Notenik collection. You can see all the files that make it happen on GitHub, at <a href="https://github.com/hbowie/notenik-web">github.com/hbowie/notenik-web</a>. </p>
<h4 id="wiki-links-now-attempt-pluralization">Wiki Links Now Attempt Pluralization</h4>
<p>Since it is often tempting to title a Note using the plural form of a word &#8211; but also common to want to refer to that Note using the singular form &#8211; if a <a href="https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/wiki-style-links.html">wiki-style link</a> does not immediately find its target, an &apos;s&apos; will be added to the link internally, and the resulting Note will be used as the target, if such a Note exists. </p>
<h4 id="markdown-quote-sharing-now-respects-work-title-lookup">Markdown Quote Sharing Now Respects Work Title Lookup</h4>
<p>One of the options for sharing a Note is to format a quote in Markdown. But I noticed recently, after updating my Commonplace Book to look up work and author information in separate Collections, that not all of the information about the author&apos;s work was being included. This has now been fixed. </p>
<h4 id="added-quick-export-and-open-command">Added Quick Export and Open Command</h4>
<p>There&apos;s a new command at the bottom of the <code>File</code> menu to perform a <code>Quick Export and Open</code>. This command will execute immediately, and perform the following sequence of actions. </p>
<ol>
<li>Export the current Collection in comma-separated values format; </li>
<li>Automatically name the output file <code>export.csv</code>; </li>
<li>Automatically place the output file in a Collection subfolder named <code>quick-export</code>; </li>
<li>Ask the operating system to open the resulting output file using whatever application is your standard for editing <code>.csv</code> files (for me, this is Apple&apos;s Numbers app). </li>
</ol>
<p>This command gives you a quick and easy way to view your Collection in the traditional rows-and-columns view associated with spreadsheets. </p>
<h4 id="object-of-a-merge-template-set-command-can-now-include-a-variable">Object of a Merge Template Set Command can now include a Variable</h4>
<p>One of the things I wanted to do when building the new Notenik.app site was to highlight the active link in the Navigation Bar. Normally this would mean that you would have to use JavaScript to modify the styling of the Nav Bar, depending on which page you were on, or would have to customize the coding of the Nav Bar for each different page on the site. But I didn&apos;t really want to do either of those things. </p>
<p>My Nav Bars (primary on top, secondary below) are coded in a couple of include files, so that I can pull them into each page as it is built. But then I needed to vary the CSS class specified for each item, depending on which page I was building. I could use a different global variable for each item, and then set the active one to a different class, in order to highlight it. It turns out (I had to check the code to verify) that a global variable specified in a primary file will be passed into include files, so that they can be referenced there. But then, how to set the global variables in a neat way, with a minimum amount of code? </p>
<p>Here&apos;s what I came up with, for inclusion in the content template file. </p>
<pre>
<code>&amp;lt;?set index-class = another-page ?&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;?set links-class = another-page ?&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;?set news-class = another-page ?&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;?set docs-class = another-page ?&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;?set about-class = another-page ?&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;?set connect-class = another-page ?&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;?set license-class = another-page ?&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;?set privacy-class = another-page ?&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;?set support-class = another-page ?&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;?set =$title$=-class = current-page ?&amp;gt;
</code></pre>
<p>Do you see what I&apos;m doing there? I first set the class for each nav item to its default value. </p>
<p>And then, with that last set command, I use the <code>title</code> variable &#8211; within the name of the global variable being set! &#8211; to change the appropriate class variable to the name of the class to use for highlighting. </p>
<p>It&apos;s kind of a neat solution. But it wouldn&apos;t have worked with earlier versions of Notenik, because the object of the set command &#8211; the name of the global variable to be set &#8211; couldn&apos;t include a variable! </p>
<p>But now it can! </p>
<h4 id="enjoy">Enjoy!</h4>
<p>Hope you enjoy the new release! If you have questions or problems or suggestions for further improvements, just send me an email at <a href="mailto:hbowie@notenik.app">hbowie@notenik.app</a>, and I&apos;ll get back to you as quickly as I can. </p>

		  ]]>
	  </content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
	  <title>Notenik 7.1.0 - Taking Dark Mode All the Way</title>
	  <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.1.0-taking-dark-mode-all-the-way.html"/>
	  <id>https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/notenik-7.1.0-taking-dark-mode-all-the-way.html</id>
	  <published>2021-08-31T09:00:00Z</published>
	  <updated>2021-08-31T12:00:00Z</updated>
	  <author>
		<name>Herb Bowie</name>
		<uri>https://hbowie.net/</uri>
	  </author>
	  <summary>
		  Notenik has mostly supported Dark Mode from the beginning &#8211; everywhere except on the Display tab, where the default was still to show black text on a white background. Now the Display Tab will follow your light/dark preferences, along with the rest of the App. 
	  </summary>
	  <content type="html">
		  <![CDATA[
		  <h4 id="turning-to-the-dark-side-on-the-display-tab">Turning to the Dark Side on the Display Tab</h4>
<p>I was kind of a late adopter of the <a href="https://support.apple.com/guide/mac-help/use-a-light-or-dark-appearance-mchl52e1c2d2/mac">Dark Appearance Setting on the Mac</a>. </p>
<p>At first I just didn&apos;t see the point. </p>
<p>But I kept trying it out until it started to grow on me a bit. </p>
<p>Until now I&apos;m using it all the time, and turning on the light setting now seems a bit of a shock. </p>
<p>Notenik has mostly supported Dark Mode from the beginning &#8211; everywhere except on the Display tab, where the default was still to show black text on a white background. </p>
<p>The reason for this was a little bit complex. I&apos;m using the Mac&apos;s WebKit API to format the Display tab, which means I&apos;m essentially formatting each Note display as a Web page &#8211; and I hadn&apos;t yet incorporated the latest HTML to allow the page to follow the user&apos;s wishes in terms of the light/dark setting. </p>
<p>But Notenik 7.1.0 fixes all that. As a bonus, when you use one of Notenik&apos;s functions to generate an actual Web page from a single Note or a Collection, the generated pages will also include the code to respect the user&apos;s preferences. </p>
<p>I think the results look pretty sharp, if I do say so myself. </p>
<p>(Of course, you can still supply your own CSS if you&apos;d prefer different colors.) </p>
<h4 id="highlighting-search-text-matches">Highlighting Search Text Matches</h4>
<p>Another new feature in 7.1.0 that also shows up on the Display tab is highlighting of matching text when you execute a Search function. Previously Notenik would take you to the Note(s) containing the text you were searching for, but would not show you where the text was found. For a brief Note, this wasn&apos;t usually a problem, but for longer Notes, it could be a bit frustrating to try to figure out where the matching text had been found. With 7.1.0, the matching text will be clearly highlighted. </p>
<h4 id="generating-wikipedia-links">Generating Wikipedia Links</h4>
<p>The final little goodie in this release is the ability to automatically populate a Link field by taking the Title of a Note and then transforming it into a Link to the English Wikipedia page on that topic. Not everyone will find this feature useful, but if you have a Collection of your favorite Authors, for example, it can be handy for populating a Link field for each author. You can find this new function within the Note menu, about halfway down the list. </p>
<h4 id="enjoy">Enjoy!</h4>
<p>Hope you enjoy the new release! If you have questions or problems or suggestions for further improvements, just send me an email at <a href="mailto:hbowie@notenik.app">hbowie@notenik.app</a>, and I&apos;ll get back to you as quickly as I can. </p>

		  ]]>
	  </content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
	  <title>Notenik 7.0.0 - The Introduction of Lookup Fields</title>
	  <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.0.0-the-introduction-of-lookup-fields.html"/>
	  <id>https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/notenik-7.0.0-the-introduction-of-lookup-fields.html</id>
	  <published>2021-08-27T09:00:00Z</published>
	  <updated>2021-08-27T12:00:00Z</updated>
	  <author>
		<name>Herb Bowie</name>
		<uri>https://hbowie.net/</uri>
	  </author>
	  <summary>
		  A field in one Collection can now reference information in other Collections. 
	  </summary>
	  <content type="html">
		  <![CDATA[
		  <p>Released on August 27, 2021 </p>
<h4 id="addition-of-a-lookup-field-type">Addition of a Lookup Field Type</h4>
<p>Users can now add <a href="../knowledge-base/EPUB/html/lookup.html">Lookup</a> fields to a Collection to reference information in another Collection. See the new <a href="../knowledge-base/EPUB/html/lookup.html">Lookup</a> field type for further info. </p>
<h4 id="improved-web-book-generation">Improved Web Book Generation</h4>
<p>Files are no longer overwritten if they haven&apos;t changed. </p>

		  ]]>
	  </content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
	  <title>Notenik 6.9.0 - Enhanced OPML Import and Export</title>
	  <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://notenik.app/news/notenik-6.9.0-enhanced-opml-import-and-export.html"/>
	  <id>https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/notenik-6.9.0-enhanced-opml-import-and-export.html</id>
	  <published>2021-08-12T09:00:00Z</published>
	  <updated>2021-08-12T12:00:00Z</updated>
	  <author>
		<name>Herb Bowie</name>
		<uri>https://hbowie.net/</uri>
	  </author>
	  <summary>
		  Added several new options to better support outlining: OPML Export, ability to add a new Child to an existing Note, plus ability to drag and drop within a sequenced list; fixed list scrolling so that the Note highlighted and visible on the left will generally match the Note currently selected on the right. 
	  </summary>
	  <content type="html">
		  <![CDATA[
		  <h4 id="added-opml-import-function">Added OPML Import Function</h4>
<p>An OPML Outline file can now be imported into Notenik. See <a href="../knowledge-base/EPUB/html/assemble-an-outline.html">Assemble an Outline</a> for more info. </p>
<h4 id="enhanced-opml-export-function">Enhanced OPML Export Function</h4>
<p>The export will now nest <code>outline</code> elements based on <a href="../knowledge-base/EPUB/html/level.html">Level</a> field values. </p>
<h4 id="added-aposnew-childapos-option-to-list-tab-popup-menu">Added &apos;New Child&apos; Option to List tab Popup Menu</h4>
<p>When using the Seq and Level fields, added an option to the Notes List popup menu to add a New Child to an existing Note, so that the Level field will be incremented by 1, and the Seq value will have a <code>.1</code> added to it. </p>
<h4 id="added-ability-to-drag-and-drop-within-a-sequenced-list">Added Ability to Drag and Drop Within a Sequenced List</h4>
<p>If you have a Sequenced Collection, you can perform some basic resequencing by dragging and dropping a Note from one position to another on the List tab. Note that you must move the Drop indicator to a line above and/or below existing Notes in order to indicate a desired new position for an existing Note. Only the Note being dragged and dropped will have its Seq value changed. </p>
<h4 id="improved-list-scrolling">Improved List Scrolling</h4>
<p>In most cases, the list view on the left should now scroll to show the selected Note displayed on the right. </p>

		  ]]>
	  </content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
	  <title>Notenik 6.8.0 - Short IDs and Concatenated Exports</title>
	  <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://notenik.app/news/notenik-6.8.0-short-ids-and-concatenated-exports.html"/>
	  <id>https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/notenik-6.8.0-short-ids-and-concatenated-exports.html</id>
	  <published>2021-08-02T09:00:00Z</published>
	  <updated>2021-08-02T12:00:00Z</updated>
	  <author>
		<name>Herb Bowie</name>
		<uri>https://hbowie.net/</uri>
	  </author>
	  <summary>
		  Added Short ID to the list of available field labels and types, to help with URL shortening; added new option to export an entire Collection into a single HTML or Markdown document; fixed a bug affecting automatic links in footnotes. 
	  </summary>
	  <content type="html">
		  <![CDATA[
		  <h4 id="added-short-id-field-label-and-type">Added Short ID Field Label and Type</h4>
<p>Added <a href="../knowledge-base/EPUB/html/short-id.html">Short ID</a> to the list of available <a href="../knowledge-base/EPUB/html/field-labels-and-types.html">Field Labels and Types</a>. One potential use for such a field, when creating a website, would be to perform your own homegrown <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/URL_shortening">URL shortening</a>, rather than using a third-party service.  </p>
<h4 id="added-new-export-option-to-concatenate-html-or-markdown">Added New Export Option to Concatenate HTML or Markdown</h4>
<p>The new options, described on the <a href="../knowledge-base/EPUB/html/import-and-export-your-notes.html">Import and Export Your Notes</a> page, will write out a single file for an entire Collection, concatenating all of the Notes in the Collection. </p>
<h4 id="fixed-a-footnote-bug">Fixed a Footnote Bug</h4>
<p><a href="../knowledge-base/EPUB/html/footnotes.html">Footnotes</a> were not being properly handled when they contained an automatic link (contained within angle brackets). This has now been corrected. </p>

		  ]]>
	  </content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
	  <title>Notenik 6.7.0 - 6.7.4 - MathJax!</title>
	  <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://notenik.app/news/notenik-6.7.0-6.7.4-mathjax.html"/>
	  <id>https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/notenik-6.7.0-6.7.4-mathjax.html</id>
	  <published>2021-07-19T09:00:00Z</published>
	  <updated>2021-07-19T12:00:00Z</updated>
	  <author>
		<name>Herb Bowie</name>
		<uri>https://hbowie.net/</uri>
	  </author>
	  <summary>
		  Added support for Mathjax; enhanced Table of Contents generation for a single Note; enhanced Table of Contents generation for an entire Collection. 
	  </summary>
	  <content type="html">
		  <![CDATA[
		  <h4 id="added-mathjax-support">Added MathJax Support</h4>
<p>Added an option to the Collection Preferences to enable <a href="../knowledge-base/EPUB/html/mathjax-support.html">MathJax Support</a>. This will be disabled by default. A copy of MathJax is now included within the app, so that Internet access is not required in order for MathJax to work. Various bugs in my MathJax implementation were straightened out in the 6.7.1 through 6.7.4 versions. </p>
<h4 id="enhanced-table-of-contents-generation">Enhanced Table of Contents Generation</h4>
<p>Enhanced Notenik&apos;s ability to <a href="../knowledge-base/EPUB/html/generate-a-note-table-of-contents.html">generate a Note Table of Contents</a>. Multiple syntax variations are now supported. Also added the ability to limit both the upper and lower range of heading level numbers to be included in the ToC. Also enhanced/corrected the code generated for a multi-level table of contents. </p>
<h4 id="enhanced-collection-table-of-contents-generation">Enhanced Collection Table of Contents Generation</h4>
<p>Added lowest- and highest-level options to the <a href="../knowledge-base/EPUB/html/generate-a-collection-table-of-contents.html">generate a Collection Table of Contents</a> command. </p>

		  ]]>
	  </content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
	  <title>Notenik 6.6.0 - Generate a Web Book</title>
	  <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://notenik.app/news/notenik-6.6.0-generate-a-web-book.html"/>
	  <id>https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/notenik-6.6.0-generate-a-web-book.html</id>
	  <published>2021-07-14T09:00:00Z</published>
	  <updated>2021-07-14T12:00:00Z</updated>
	  <author>
		<name>Herb Bowie</name>
		<uri>https://hbowie.net/</uri>
	  </author>
	  <summary>
		  Added a new Markdown extension to generate a Table of Contents for an entire Collection; added another new Markdown extension to generate an Index for an entire Collection; added another new Markdown extensions to generate a Tags Outline; added a new command to Generate a Web Book from a Collection; updated the Notenik Knowledge Base to make use of all of these new features. 
	  </summary>
	  <content type="html">
		  <![CDATA[
		  <h4 id="added-markdown-extension-for-a-collection-table-of-contents">Added Markdown Extension for a Collection Table of Contents</h4>
<p>Users may now insert a line containing <code>{:collection-toc}</code> into the body of a Note in order to have that line replaced with a complete Table of Contents for the entire Collection containing the Note. See <a href="../knowledge-base/EPUB/html/generate-a-collection-table-of-contents.html">Generate a Collection Table of Contents</a> for further details. </p>
<h4 id="added-markdown-extension-for-a-collection-index">Added Markdown Extension for a Collection Index</h4>
<p>Users may now insert a line containing <code>{:index}</code> into the Body of a Note in order to have that line replaced with an Index for the entire Collection containing the Note. See <a href="../knowledge-base/EPUB/html/generate-a-collection-index.html">Generate a Collection Index</a> for further details. </p>
<h4 id="added-markdown-extension-for-a-tags-outline">Added Markdown Extension for a Tags Outline</h4>
<p>Users may now insert a line containing <code>{:tags-outline}</code> into the Body of a Note in order to have that line replaced with an outline of all the Tags used in the entire Collection, along with the Notes bearing each Tag. See <a href="../knowledge-base/EPUB/html/generate-a-tags-outline.html">Generate a Tags Outline</a> for further details. </p>
<h4 id="added-alternative-syntax-for-a-note-table-of-contents">Added Alternative Syntax for a Note Table of Contents</h4>
<p>A Table of Contents for an individual Note can now be generated by inserting a line containing <code>{:toc}</code> (as an alternative to <code>[toc]</code>) into the Body of the Note. The alternative syntax was added for consistency with new Markdown extensions added in this release, and described above. See <a href="../knowledge-base/EPUB/html/generate-a-note-table-of-contents.html">Generate a Note Table of Contents</a> for further details. </p>
<h4 id="added-generate-web-book-command">Added Generate Web Book Command</h4>
<p>Added a new command beneath the <code>File</code> menu to <a href="../knowledge-base/EPUB/html/generate-a-web-book.html">Generate a Web Book</a>. This command can make use of the other new Notenik features listed above. </p>

		  ]]>
	  </content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
	  <title>Notenik 6.5.0 - Added What&apos;s New Menu Option</title>
	  <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://notenik.app/news/notenik-6.5.0-added-whats-new-menu-option.html"/>
	  <id>https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/notenik-6.5.0-added-whats-new-menu-option.html</id>
	  <published>2021-07-07T09:00:00Z</published>
	  <updated>2021-07-07T12:00:00Z</updated>
	  <author>
		<name>Herb Bowie</name>
		<uri>https://hbowie.net/</uri>
	  </author>
	  <summary>
		  Added an option to backup an entire Collection to a compressed Zip file; made improvements to Streamlined Reading, to focus only on Seq, Title and Body fields; expanded the custom URL help command to allow an ID to be included, to point to a specific Note to be initially displayed; added a What&apos;s New command beneath the Help menu to show the user the latest changes to the app. 
	  </summary>
	  <content type="html">
		  <![CDATA[
		  <h4 id="added-whataposs-new-command-beneath-the-help-menu">Added What&apos;s New Command beneath the Help Menu</h4>
<p>Selecting <code>What&amp;apos;s New</code> beneath the <code>Help</code> menu will open the Notenik Knowledge Base and position it on the Note showing Notenik&apos;s latest changes. </p>
<h4 id="added-backup-to-zip-option">Added Backup to Zip option</h4>
<p>A new option beneath the File menu will create a Zip file containing a compressed backup of the entire current Collection. </p>
<h4 id="improvements-to-streamlined-reading">Improvements to Streamlined Reading</h4>
<p>Only the Seq, Title and Body fields are now included on the Display tab, when Streamlined Reading is chosen for the Collection. </p>
<h4 id="help-command-expanded">Help Command Expanded</h4>
<p>A notenik Custom URL invoking the help command can now optionally specify the ID of a specific Note to be displayed, after opening the Knowledge Base. </p>

		  ]]>
	  </content>
	</entry>
</feed>
