<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Notenik News</title>
  <subtitle>The latest news about the Notenik app</subtitle>
  <link href="https://notenik.app/atom.xml" type="application/atom+xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://notenik.app/" type="text/html" rel="alternate"  />
  <updated>2022-01-12T09:00:00Z</updated>
  <rights>Copyright © 2022, Herb Bowie</rights>
  <author>
	<name>Herb Bowie</name>
  </author>
  <id>https://hbowie.net/atom.xml</id>
	<entry>
	  <title>Notenik 7.9.0 - Taking Outlining to a New Level</title>
	  <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.9.0-taking-outlining-to-a-new-level.html"/>
	  <id>https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/notenik-7.9.0-taking-outlining-to-a-new-level.html</id>
	  <published>2022-01-04T09:00:00Z</published>
	  <updated>2022-01-04T12:00:00Z</updated>
	  <author>
		<name>Herb Bowie</name>
		<uri>https://hbowie.net/</uri>
	  </author>
	  <summary>
		  This release includes a powerful new function for renumbering the Seq values for a range of Notes, indent and outdent commands, and some improvements to Web Book publishing. With these new options, outlining in Notenik is more powerful than ever. 
	  </summary>
	  <content type="html">
		  <![CDATA[
		  <p>Notenik was never intended to be an outliner, but outlining has sort of gradually crept into the app over the last six months or so, starting with the <a href="https://notenik.app/news/notenik-6.3.0-leveraging-the-new-level-field.html">introduction of the Level field in Notenik 6.3.0</a> . </p>
<p>Version 7.9.0 adds a couple of finishing touches that were missing before. </p>
<p>First of all, if you select a range of Notes (in a Collection sorted by <code>Seq + Title</code>, and containing Seq and Level fields), and then right-click to open the context menu for the List tab, you&apos;ll see an option that says <code>Modify Seq&amp;hellip;</code>. If you select this function, then you&apos;ll see a new window that allows you to specify a new Seq value for the first Note in the range. Click OK after entering that new value, and the entire range will be renumbered, with Notes following the first falling into line behind their leader, maintaining the same outline structure, but changing Seq and Level values appropriately. It&apos;s quite a powerful way to restructure an outline in Notenik, and brings Notenik a bit closer to having most of what one might need when working on an outline. </p>
<p>Next, there are new <code>Indent</code> and <code>Outdent</code> commands to be found beneath the <code>Note</code> menu, with appropriate keyboard shortcuts. </p>
<p>And then the way Web Book publication works has been improved. It&apos;s now just another export format, instead of a separate entry beneath the <code>File</code> menu. And, when generating a Web Book as a Site, the first page now gets written out twice, once with the file name of <code>index.html</code>. This removes the need for the ability to generate a redirection page for the first page, and so that option has been retired. </p>
<p>There&apos;s now an impressive array of functionality in Notenik to aid in outlining, and I&apos;ve updated the page on outlining in the Knowledge Base to collect all of this together in one place: see <a href="https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/using-notenik-as-an-outliner.html">Using Notenik as an Outliner</a> for all of the details. </p>
<p>And that does it for the first release of 2022! As always, if you have something on your Notenik wish list that is still not there, feel free to <a href="mailto:support@notenik.app">drop me a line</a> and let me know how you think my little app can be further improved. I&apos;m always happy to entertain suggestions from users. </p>

		  ]]>
	  </content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
	  <title>Notenik 7.8.0 - Improvements to Streamlined Reading and Web Books</title>
	  <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.8.0-improvements-to-streamlined-reading-and-web-books.html"/>
	  <id>https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/notenik-7.8.0-improvements-to-streamlined-reading-and-web-books.html</id>
	  <published>2021-12-13T09:00:00Z</published>
	  <updated>2021-12-13T12:00:00Z</updated>
	  <author>
		<name>Herb Bowie</name>
		<uri>https://hbowie.net/</uri>
	  </author>
	  <summary>
		  This release includes a new Notenik Intro, the addition of a new, optional header line when publishing a Web Book, a new <code>Include Children</code> field useful when using outlining with streamlined reading, and a new Sort option to view things in pure Date order (irrespective of Status). 
	  </summary>
	  <content type="html">
		  <![CDATA[
		  <p>I received some requests recently for a kinder, gentler introduction to Notenik that would include some visuals, in addition to the words. </p>
<p>So with this release a new &quot;Notenik Intro&quot; has been introduced. You can experience it in one of several ways: </p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>As with the full <a href="https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/notenik-knowledge-base.html">Notenik Knowledge Base</a>, the new <a href="https://notenik.app/intro/EPUB/html/welcome-to-notenik.html">Notenik Intro</a> has been published as a Web Book that is available on the <a href="https://notenik.app/index.html">Notenik.app</a> website. </p>
</li>
<li>
<p>If you&apos;re firing up Notenik for the very first time, then you should see the Intro opened for you automatically, in edit mode, so that you can browse through it, but also edit it as desired to use as your first Notenik Collection, if you&apos;d like. </p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Whenever you create a New Collection, you&apos;ll see the Notenik Intro available as a starting option. </p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>With the addition of the new Intro, this meant that the Notenik.app website now contained two different Web Books: one for the full Knowledge Base, and one for the Intro. So I fixed something else that had been bugging me for a while, and added an optional header line that could be included when generating a Web Book. You can see this in action by viewing either (or both!) of these documents on the website. I&apos;ve used this top line to contain a book title on the left, and a link back to the full website on the right. I think you&apos;ll agree that the addition of this header line makes these web books easier to use. </p>
<p>This release includes one more feature useful for Streamlined Reading and Web Books: a new field titled <code>Include Children</code>. I haven&apos;t made use of it yet for either of the Notenik Web Books, so I can&apos;t point you to an example, but it allows you to pull the children of a Note into the parent&apos;s Display, in cases where you might wish the child Notes to be separately addressable, but don&apos;t want to make the reader keep clicking on a &quot;Next&quot; link to advance from one to the next. </p>
<p>And then, finally, I&apos;ve added a new Sort option that allows a Collection to be sorted by Date (without respect to Status) plus the Seq field (if used) followed by the Title field. I had a user request this feature, and it seemed reasonable to me, so there it is. </p>
<p>Those are the changes in the latest release. Check them out in the app and, where you need more info to make sense of them, refer to the Notenik Knowledge Base for the details. And if you have something on your Notenik wish list that is still not there, feel free to <a href="mailto:support@notenik.app">drop me a line</a> and let me know how you think my little app can be further improved. I&apos;m always happy to entertain suggestions from users. </p>

		  ]]>
	  </content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
	  <title>Notenik 7.7.0 - Class Templates are Introduced</title>
	  <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.7.0-class-templates-are-introduced.html"/>
	  <id>https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/notenik-7.7.0-class-templates-are-introduced.html</id>
	  <published>2021-11-30T09:00:00Z</published>
	  <updated>2021-11-30T12:00:00Z</updated>
	  <author>
		<name>Herb Bowie</name>
		<uri>https://hbowie.net/</uri>
	  </author>
	  <summary>
		  This release introduces Class templates. Each different Class value within a Collection can have its own template, and that template can limit the fields included on the Edit tab for Notes of that Class, and can also supply default values for any fields that are included. This is one of those features that can be used in lots of different ways, for many different purposes, so it&apos;s worth sitting down and having a good think about how you might be able to put this feature to use for your Notes. 
	  </summary>
	  <content type="html">
		  <![CDATA[
		  <p>This release is focused on an expanded use of the Class field, including the introduction of the very useful Class templates. </p>
<p>The Class field was introduced in 7.5.0, and its associated features have been expanded in 7.6.0, and now again in 7.7.0. </p>
<p>With this release, Notenik will recognize a subfolder named <code>class</code>, and then use each of the files found therein as class templates. Class templates can be used for three very useful purposes. </p>
<p>First, each filename will be recognized as a valid Class value, whether or not that value was identified as such in the Collection template file. </p>
<p>Second, you can omit certain fields from a Class template file, and then only the remaining fields (the ones included in the Class template file) will be shown on the Edit tab, when that Class value is specified for a particular Note. </p>
<p>Third, you can supply default values for any of the associated fields, and these will then be pre-populated when you create a new Note with that Class. </p>
<p>A couple of these functions above involve a bit of a chicken-and-egg type problem: the Edit field will be configured and pre-populated based on the Class, but there&apos;s no way to specify the Class until you get to the Edit tab! </p>
<p>The solution here is the new command, found beneath the <code>Note</code> menu, to create a <code>New Note w/Options</code>. When you select this menu item, you will be presented with a window allowing you to select the Class for the new Note. Once you hit <code>OK</code> on this screen, you will be taken to the Edit tab, blank except for the values you&apos;ve specified. </p>
<p>This new Options screen also allows you to fill in a couple of other useful fields. First, the Note&apos;s title, just because that seems a natural thing to do at this point in your flow. But then there are also the Level and Seq fields for the new Note. The Level field will default to that of the last Note selected before invoking this screen, but you can change it if you like. The Seq field will then change appropriately to reflect the Level you&apos;ve selected, in order to place the new Note just after the last Note selected. </p>
<p>Notenik also has some new Display logic associated with certain special Class values, especially when a Collection is in the Streamlined Reading mode. For example, a Class value of <code>quote</code> will result in the body of the Note being displayed with <code>blockquote</code> styling. And if you use the new <code>Attribution</code> field to indicate the source of the quote, that field will be neatly shown below the quotation itself. </p>
<p>As long as I was allowing a Class template to limit the fields shown on the Edit tab, it also seemed like a good time to remove calculated fields from the Edit tab, since they can&apos;t be modified directly by the user anyway. So now the Edit tab will be that much cleaner, allowing you to focus on the fields of interest to you. </p>
<p>Those are the heavy hitters in this release. Be sure and read more about these new features in the Notenik Knowledge Base, where you&apos;ll find all the details. And if you have something on your Notenik wish list that is still not there, feel free to <a href="mailto:support@notenik.app">drop me a line</a> and let me know how you think my little app can be further improved. I&apos;m always happy to entertain suggestions from users. </p>

		  ]]>
	  </content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
	  <title>Notenik 7.6.0 - A Little Something for Everyone</title>
	  <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.6.0-a-little-something-for-everyone.html"/>
	  <id>https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/notenik-7.6.0-a-little-something-for-everyone.html</id>
	  <published>2021-11-09T09:00:00Z</published>
	  <updated>2021-11-09T12:00:00Z</updated>
	  <author>
		<name>Herb Bowie</name>
		<uri>https://hbowie.net/</uri>
	  </author>
	  <summary>
		  Notenik 7.6.0 should contain a little something for everyone, including some additional sort options, an improvement to the Quick Action window, more reasonable handling of data from deleted fields, the ability to include images in a Web Book, as well as the ability to specify your own available values for the new Class field. 
	  </summary>
	  <content type="html">
		  <![CDATA[
		  <p>This is another grab bag release, with a handful of unrelated changes, but everyone should find a little something useful in the mix. Some of these changes were suggested by users, and some were ones I dreamt up all on my own. </p>
<p>First of all, a Sort Option to sequence your list by Date Modified has been added. No matter what sort of information you&apos;re storing in Notenik, it will probably at least occasionally be useful to sort your Notes to see those that have most recently been modified. This was a user request. </p>
<p>Next, I&apos;ve added a keyboard shortcut to the option to Reverse a Sort. Combining the CMD key with a number key will change the sort field used for a Collection to one of the nine available options. (See the Sort submenu beneath the Collection menu for details.) But now <code>CMD 0</code> will reverse the sequence for any of these options. Especially when switching from one option to another, I often find I want to reverse the sequence, and so this new keyboard shortcut makes that a snap. </p>
<p>Another user request was to have the Quick Action window retain the last Collection Shortcut entered as a default for the next time a Quick Action is taken. This can make an action even quicker, and I&apos;m already using it to speed up some of my Notenik work. </p>
<p>One more change in this release involves the removal of fields from a Collection. This isn&apos;t the most common of operations &#8211; usually you&apos;re selecting fields when you create a new Collection, or adding more later. But occasionally, after I&apos;ve added some fields, I later realize that they&apos;re not really needed and, in fact, are just getting in the way. At that point I open the Collection Preferences and uncheck the fields I no longer want. So far, so good, it would seem. But what if some of your Notes already have data in those now-deleted fields? Unfortunately, Notenik did not previously have a systematic way for dealing with this sort of abandoned data. With this release, though, those fields and values will be systematically purged from your Notes, to prevent any untoward things from happening somewhere downstream. This is not a feature you&apos;ll be using every day, I&apos;ll wager, but good to know it&apos;s there when you need it. </p>
<p>And then there&apos;s yet another change in this release, only useful if you&apos;re using the recently added option to <code>Generate a Web Book</code>. In that case, the <code>Image Name</code> field can now be used to include an image that will appear towards the top of a page, between the <code>Title</code> and the <code>Body</code>. </p>
<p>And then the new <code>Class</code> field has been fleshed out a little further, with the user given an option for specifying his or her own values for the field, as an alternative to the ones that seem useful to me. Still more to come in terms of functionality associated with this field, but this is a small step forward. </p>
<p>And that&apos;s it! Hope you find something useful here. And if you have something on your Notenik wish list that is still not there, feel free to <a href="mailto:support@notenik.app">drop me a line</a> and let me know how you think my little app can be further improved. I&apos;m always happy to entertain suggestions from users. </p>

		  ]]>
	  </content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
	  <title>Notenik 7.5.0 - A Few Small Improvements</title>
	  <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.5.0-a-few-small-improvements.html"/>
	  <id>https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/notenik-7.5.0-a-few-small-improvements.html</id>
	  <published>2021-10-28T09:00:00Z</published>
	  <updated>2021-10-28T12:00:00Z</updated>
	  <author>
		<name>Herb Bowie</name>
		<uri>https://hbowie.net/</uri>
	  </author>
	  <summary>
		  Notenik 7.5.0 makes a few small improvements, including reorganizing some of the app&apos;s menus, as well as rearranging things on the Collection Prefs screen. The Advanced Search option is the new feature that might be most widely appreciated. 
	  </summary>
	  <content type="html">
		  <![CDATA[
		  <p>Sometimes it&apos;s enough to just improve a few things for users, rather than adding a bunch of completely new stuff. </p>
<p>This release adds an Advanced Search function. The new window allows you to opt out of including certain common fields in a search, when you&apos;re looking for more focused results. It also gives you the option of doing a case-sensitive search. These are not options you need everyday, but it&apos;s nice to have them there when they&apos;d be helpful.  </p>
<p>Adding a new menu option made me rethink Notenik&apos;s overall menu structure, resulting in a couple of changes that should make everything a little easier to navigate. If you&apos;re looking for sort options, these are now found beneath the Collection menu. Search options, including the new Advanced Search option, are now beneath the new Nav menu, along with a few more navigation options. And the Format menu is now gone, with the <code>Display Appearance</code> option now beneath the App preferences. </p>
<p>This release also adds a new field label and type of <code>Class</code>. The intent here is to have a field that tells Notenik something about the intended role of a particular Note within the overall structure of a Collection. But this is mostly a placeholder for now. Look for future enhancements in coming releases to more fully express my design intent here. </p>
<p>In the meantime, though, the addition of this new field was the proverbial straw that broke the camel&apos;s back when it came to the Collection Preferences window, so I&apos;ve reorganized this thing a bit to make it easier to use, and make better use of available screen real estate. </p>
<p>A new user recently noticed that, if you have the Edit tab visible, Notenik allows you to quit the application, or close the window, without saving any in-flight changes you had made. I&apos;ve fixed this, so Notenik will save your changes automatically in this scenario. </p>
<p>And then, one more slight improvement: when sorting by the Seq field, Notenik will now perform padding on up to six segments (separated by dots or dashes), whereas before it stopped at four. </p>
<p>If you&apos;re a Notenik user, then hopefully you will find at least a few of these refinements to be helpful. </p>

		  ]]>
	  </content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
	  <title>Notenik 7.4.0 - Wiki Link Enhancements</title>
	  <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.4.0-wiki-link-enhancements.html"/>
	  <id>https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/notenik-7.4.0-wiki-link-enhancements.html</id>
	  <published>2021-10-14T09:00:00Z</published>
	  <updated>2021-10-14T12:00:00Z</updated>
	  <author>
		<name>Herb Bowie</name>
		<uri>https://hbowie.net/</uri>
	  </author>
	  <summary>
		  Notenik 7.4.0 addresses some common issues that often arise when making use of  Wiki Style Links. Welcome to backlinks, automatic target note creation, and AKA entries for your Notes! 
	  </summary>
	  <content type="html">
		  <![CDATA[
		  <p>Notenik 7.4.0 addresses some common issues that often arise when making use of  <a href="https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/wiki-style-links.html">Wiki Style Links</a>. </p>
<p><strong>Issue # 1</strong>: You&apos;re writing one Note, then realize you want that Note to link to a different Note, but that different Note does not yet exist. Before 7.4.0, Notenik would allow you to create the link but then, when you clicked on it, would just give you a (not very helpful) error message. </p>
<p>The fix? When you save a Note (or reload a Note you have edited externally, using your favorite text editor), Notenik will check all of the Note&apos;s wiki style links to make sure they point to Notes that actually exist. For any that don&apos;t yet exist, Notenik will automatically create them! And the new Note will contain a handy pointer back to the Note that created it, via its wiki style link. </p>
<p>Problem solved! </p>
<p><strong>Issue # 2</strong>: You&apos;ve named a Note one way (including a verb and an object, let&apos;s say) and then want to later refer to that Note via a wiki style link. But given the context of the reference to that Note, you want to use slightly different wording in the new sentence you&apos;re constructing (calling out just the object, let&apos;s say). </p>
<p>The solution? Now you can add a special <a href="https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/also-known-as.html">AKA</a> field to a Collection, and then add one or more alternate identifiers to a Note, allowing you to then wiki link to that Note using any of the alternates you have called out. For example, even though the <a href="https://notenik.app/docs.html">Notenik Knowledge Base</a> includes a Note for this new field that is titled &quot;Also Known As,&quot; I can link to that Note using a Wiki Link of <code>[AKA]</code>, because the <code>Also Known As</code> Note contains an <code>AKA</code> entry that calls out <code>AKA</code> as an alternate identifier for that Note. </p>
<p>Pretty handy, eh? </p>
<p><strong>Issue # 3</strong>: You&apos;ve created a bunch of wiki style links that refer to various other Notes. And now you&apos;re looking at a Note in your Collection. And you can see what other Notes are linked to from this Note, but then you wonder&hellip; which Notes, if any, link to this Note? </p>
<p>The answer? <em>Backlinks!</em> By enabling the new field type called <a href="https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/back-links.html">Backlinks</a>, Notenik will automatically keep track of backlinks in your Collection, and make them available on the Display tab. </p>
<p>And so now you have automatic bidirectional linking of Notes within a Collection: write one link to go from one Note to another, and you can then automatically traverse your wiki style links in either direction. </p>
<p><strong>And One More Thing</strong>: The Notenik Knowledge Base now has a new article in the <a href="https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/putting-it-all-together.html">Putting It All Together</a> section called <a href="https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/write-a-web-book.html">Write a Web Book</a>, that gives you some pointers on how to create a web book of your own. Hope you find it useful! </p>

		  ]]>
	  </content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
	  <title>Notenik 7.3.0 - A Handful of Helpful Refinements</title>
	  <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.3.0-a-handful-of-helpful-refinements.html"/>
	  <id>https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/notenik-7.3.0-a-handful-of-helpful-refinements.html</id>
	  <published>2021-09-30T09:00:00Z</published>
	  <updated>2021-09-30T12:00:00Z</updated>
	  <author>
		<name>Herb Bowie</name>
		<uri>https://hbowie.net/</uri>
	  </author>
	  <summary>
		  Version 7.3.0 of Notenik includes a handful of nifty changes: Improved Seq and Level Defaults for Drag and Drop; Improved Recognition of Parent Realm Folders; Parent Realm Folders Now Appear on Open Recent Menu; Streamlined New Collection process; Saving Security-Scoped Bookmarks; and Undo Provided for Note Deletions. 
	  </summary>
	  <content type="html">
		  <![CDATA[
		  <p>Version 7.3.0 of Notenik includes a handful of helpful improvements. </p>
<h5 id="improved-seq-and-level-defaults-for-drag-and-drop">Improved Seq and Level Defaults for Drag and Drop</h5>
<p>When pasting an item (such as a URL) into a List sorted by Seq, and when the drop point is between existing rows, Notenik will now do a better job of setting reasonable defaults for both Seq and Level for the new Note. </p>
<h5 id="improved-recognition-of-parent-realm-folders">Improved Recognition of Parent Realm Folders</h5>
<p>Notenik allows you to drag a folder to be opened onto its app icon in the dock. That folder can be either a Notenik Collection or a parent folder containing Notenik Collections. Before this change, if a folder contained a single text file named <code>robots.txt</code>, then that would be treated as a Note, and so the folder would be opened as a Collection. After this change, such a folder will be more productively treated as the object of an <a href="https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/open-parent-realm.html">Open Parent Realm</a> command. </p>
<h5 id="parent-realm-folders-now-appear-on-open-recent-menu">Parent Realm Folders Now Appear on Open Recent Menu</h5>
<p>After you execute the <a href="https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/open-parent-realm.html">Open Parent Realm</a> command (either explicitly via the <code>File</code> menu, or implicitly by dragging a folder onto the app icon), the Parent Realm folder will now be added to the the <code>Open Recent</code> menu, making it available to be easily reopened later. </p>
<h5 id="streamlined-new-collection-process">Streamlined New Collection process</h5>
<p>It seemed a bit confusing to have so many different options for creating a new Collection, so I&apos;ve combined them. Now there is just one <code>File</code> menu option, that says <code>New Collection&amp;hellip;</code>. This option walks you through several screens where you can pick a location, pick a name, and pick a Collection type, and then shows you the Collection Preferences screen where you can make any final adjustments to the configuration of your New Collection. </p>
<h5 id="saving-security-scoped-bookmarks">Saving Security-Scoped Bookmarks</h5>
<p>Notenik has been enhanced to try to extend the life of access permissions for Collections assigned Shortcuts, so as to reduce the number of times a user has to re-authorize access to a folder. See <a href="https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/tailor-collection-preferences.html">Tailor Collection Preferences</a> for info on assigning a Shortcut to a Collection. </p>
<h5 id="undo-provided-for-note-deletions">Undo Provided for Note Deletions</h5>
<p>If you delete a Note by mistake, then you can use the Undo function (beneath the Edit menu) to undo the deletion, with the only caveat being that any note attachments will not be restored. </p>

		  ]]>
	  </content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
	  <title>Notenik 7.2.0 - Some Nifty Enhancements</title>
	  <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.2.0-some-nifty-enhancements.html"/>
	  <id>https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/notenik-7.2.0-some-nifty-enhancements.html</id>
	  <published>2021-09-20T09:00:00Z</published>
	  <updated>2021-09-20T12:00:00Z</updated>
	  <author>
		<name>Herb Bowie</name>
		<uri>https://hbowie.net/</uri>
	  </author>
	  <summary>
		  Version 7.2.0 of Notenik includes a handful of nifty changes: the website address has been updated to point to Notenik.app; wiki links now will try to pluralize a reference, if it is not found in singular form; the Merge template Set command now allows a variable to be used as part or all of a global variable name; Markdown quote sharing corrected to respect lookup links; added a Quick Export and Open command. 
	  </summary>
	  <content type="html">
		  <![CDATA[
		  <p>Version 7.2.0 of Notenik includes a handful of nifty changes. </p>
<h4 id="new-and-improved-notenik-website">New and Improved Notenik Website</h4>
<p>The Notenik website used to reside at Notenik.net. </p>
<p>That URL will still get you there (as will Notenik.com), but the primary name for the website has now been changed to <a href="https://notenik.app/">Notenik.app</a> because &#8211; well it&apos;s all about the Notenik App! </p>
<p>More significantly, the appearance and the contents of the site have both been improved. Check it out when you get a chance! </p>
<p>And, for those of you who are interested, the Notenik site is itself generated by a Notenik collection. You can see all the files that make it happen on GitHub, at <a href="https://github.com/hbowie/notenik-web">github.com/hbowie/notenik-web</a>. </p>
<h4 id="wiki-links-now-attempt-pluralization">Wiki Links Now Attempt Pluralization</h4>
<p>Since it is often tempting to title a Note using the plural form of a word &#8211; but also common to want to refer to that Note using the singular form &#8211; if a <a href="https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/wiki-style-links.html">wiki-style link</a> does not immediately find its target, an &apos;s&apos; will be added to the link internally, and the resulting Note will be used as the target, if such a Note exists. </p>
<h4 id="markdown-quote-sharing-now-respects-work-title-lookup">Markdown Quote Sharing Now Respects Work Title Lookup</h4>
<p>One of the options for sharing a Note is to format a quote in Markdown. But I noticed recently, after updating my Commonplace Book to look up work and author information in separate Collections, that not all of the information about the author&apos;s work was being included. This has now been fixed. </p>
<h4 id="added-quick-export-and-open-command">Added Quick Export and Open Command</h4>
<p>There&apos;s a new command at the bottom of the <code>File</code> menu to perform a <code>Quick Export and Open</code>. This command will execute immediately, and perform the following sequence of actions. </p>
<ol>
<li>Export the current Collection in comma-separated values format; </li>
<li>Automatically name the output file <code>export.csv</code>; </li>
<li>Automatically place the output file in a Collection subfolder named <code>quick-export</code>; </li>
<li>Ask the operating system to open the resulting output file using whatever application is your standard for editing <code>.csv</code> files (for me, this is Apple&apos;s Numbers app). </li>
</ol>
<p>This command gives you a quick and easy way to view your Collection in the traditional rows-and-columns view associated with spreadsheets. </p>
<h4 id="object-of-a-merge-template-set-command-can-now-include-a-variable">Object of a Merge Template Set Command can now include a Variable</h4>
<p>One of the things I wanted to do when building the new Notenik.app site was to highlight the active link in the Navigation Bar. Normally this would mean that you would have to use JavaScript to modify the styling of the Nav Bar, depending on which page you were on, or would have to customize the coding of the Nav Bar for each different page on the site. But I didn&apos;t really want to do either of those things. </p>
<p>My Nav Bars (primary on top, secondary below) are coded in a couple of include files, so that I can pull them into each page as it is built. But then I needed to vary the CSS class specified for each item, depending on which page I was building. I could use a different global variable for each item, and then set the active one to a different class, in order to highlight it. It turns out (I had to check the code to verify) that a global variable specified in a primary file will be passed into include files, so that they can be referenced there. But then, how to set the global variables in a neat way, with a minimum amount of code? </p>
<p>Here&apos;s what I came up with, for inclusion in the content template file. </p>
<pre>
<code>&amp;lt;?set index-class = another-page ?&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;?set links-class = another-page ?&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;?set news-class = another-page ?&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;?set docs-class = another-page ?&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;?set about-class = another-page ?&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;?set connect-class = another-page ?&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;?set license-class = another-page ?&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;?set privacy-class = another-page ?&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;?set support-class = another-page ?&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;?set =$title$=-class = current-page ?&amp;gt;
</code></pre>
<p>Do you see what I&apos;m doing there? I first set the class for each nav item to its default value. </p>
<p>And then, with that last set command, I use the <code>title</code> variable &#8211; within the name of the global variable being set! &#8211; to change the appropriate class variable to the name of the class to use for highlighting. </p>
<p>It&apos;s kind of a neat solution. But it wouldn&apos;t have worked with earlier versions of Notenik, because the object of the set command &#8211; the name of the global variable to be set &#8211; couldn&apos;t include a variable! </p>
<p>But now it can! </p>
<h4 id="enjoy">Enjoy!</h4>
<p>Hope you enjoy the new release! If you have questions or problems or suggestions for further improvements, just send me an email at <a href="mailto:hbowie@notenik.app">hbowie@notenik.app</a>, and I&apos;ll get back to you as quickly as I can. </p>

		  ]]>
	  </content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
	  <title>Notenik 7.1.0 - Taking Dark Mode All the Way</title>
	  <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.1.0-taking-dark-mode-all-the-way.html"/>
	  <id>https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/notenik-7.1.0-taking-dark-mode-all-the-way.html</id>
	  <published>2021-08-31T09:00:00Z</published>
	  <updated>2021-08-31T12:00:00Z</updated>
	  <author>
		<name>Herb Bowie</name>
		<uri>https://hbowie.net/</uri>
	  </author>
	  <summary>
		  Notenik has mostly supported Dark Mode from the beginning &#8211; everywhere except on the Display tab, where the default was still to show black text on a white background. Now the Display Tab will follow your light/dark preferences, along with the rest of the App. 
	  </summary>
	  <content type="html">
		  <![CDATA[
		  <h4 id="turning-to-the-dark-side-on-the-display-tab">Turning to the Dark Side on the Display Tab</h4>
<p>I was kind of a late adopter of the <a href="https://support.apple.com/guide/mac-help/use-a-light-or-dark-appearance-mchl52e1c2d2/mac">Dark Appearance Setting on the Mac</a>. </p>
<p>At first I just didn&apos;t see the point. </p>
<p>But I kept trying it out until it started to grow on me a bit. </p>
<p>Until now I&apos;m using it all the time, and turning on the light setting now seems a bit of a shock. </p>
<p>Notenik has mostly supported Dark Mode from the beginning &#8211; everywhere except on the Display tab, where the default was still to show black text on a white background. </p>
<p>The reason for this was a little bit complex. I&apos;m using the Mac&apos;s WebKit API to format the Display tab, which means I&apos;m essentially formatting each Note display as a Web page &#8211; and I hadn&apos;t yet incorporated the latest HTML to allow the page to follow the user&apos;s wishes in terms of the light/dark setting. </p>
<p>But Notenik 7.1.0 fixes all that. As a bonus, when you use one of Notenik&apos;s functions to generate an actual Web page from a single Note or a Collection, the generated pages will also include the code to respect the user&apos;s preferences. </p>
<p>I think the results look pretty sharp, if I do say so myself. </p>
<p>(Of course, you can still supply your own CSS if you&apos;d prefer different colors.) </p>
<h4 id="highlighting-search-text-matches">Highlighting Search Text Matches</h4>
<p>Another new feature in 7.1.0 that also shows up on the Display tab is highlighting of matching text when you execute a Search function. Previously Notenik would take you to the Note(s) containing the text you were searching for, but would not show you where the text was found. For a brief Note, this wasn&apos;t usually a problem, but for longer Notes, it could be a bit frustrating to try to figure out where the matching text had been found. With 7.1.0, the matching text will be clearly highlighted. </p>
<h4 id="generating-wikipedia-links">Generating Wikipedia Links</h4>
<p>The final little goodie in this release is the ability to automatically populate a Link field by taking the Title of a Note and then transforming it into a Link to the English Wikipedia page on that topic. Not everyone will find this feature useful, but if you have a Collection of your favorite Authors, for example, it can be handy for populating a Link field for each author. You can find this new function within the Note menu, about halfway down the list. </p>
<h4 id="enjoy">Enjoy!</h4>
<p>Hope you enjoy the new release! If you have questions or problems or suggestions for further improvements, just send me an email at <a href="mailto:hbowie@notenik.app">hbowie@notenik.app</a>, and I&apos;ll get back to you as quickly as I can. </p>

		  ]]>
	  </content>
	</entry>
	<entry>
	  <title>Notenik 7.0.0 - The Introduction of Lookup Fields</title>
	  <link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.0.0-the-introduction-of-lookup-fields.html"/>
	  <id>https://notenik.app/knowledge-base/EPUB/html/notenik-7.0.0-the-introduction-of-lookup-fields.html</id>
	  <published>2021-08-27T09:00:00Z</published>
	  <updated>2021-08-27T12:00:00Z</updated>
	  <author>
		<name>Herb Bowie</name>
		<uri>https://hbowie.net/</uri>
	  </author>
	  <summary>
		  A field in one Collection can now reference information in other Collections. 
	  </summary>
	  <content type="html">
		  <![CDATA[
		  <p>Released on August 27, 2021 </p>
<h4 id="addition-of-a-lookup-field-type">Addition of a Lookup Field Type</h4>
<p>Users can now add <a href="../knowledge-base/EPUB/html/lookup.html">Lookup</a> fields to a Collection to reference information in another Collection. See the new <a href="../knowledge-base/EPUB/html/lookup.html">Lookup</a> field type for further info. </p>
<h4 id="improved-web-book-generation">Improved Web Book Generation</h4>
<p>Files are no longer overwritten if they haven&apos;t changed. </p>

		  ]]>
	  </content>
	</entry>
</feed>
