<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
	<title>Notenik News</title>
	<link>https://notenik.app</link>
	<description>What's New with the Notenik app?</description>
	<language>en</language>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 9.0.1 - Hooked on Notenik</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-9.0.1-hooked-on-notenik.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-9.0.1-hooked-on-notenik.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Thu, 31 Mar 2022 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  The last couple of releases focused on better integration with other apps, including new Custom URL commands, new custom AppleScript commands, and the ability to integrate with the Hook app via their official scripts.  <br />

	  </description>
	</item>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 8.8.0 - Improvements to Note Editing</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-8.8.0-improvements-to-note-editing.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-8.8.0-improvements-to-note-editing.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Fri, 18 Mar 2022 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  Added a Note Selector window that allows a user, while remaining on Display or Edit of one Note, to look up the title of a second Note, for possible insertion into the text of the first Note; also expanded the width of the Body text editing field, and made inclusion of a &apos;Body:&apos; field label optional, on the Edit tab as well as the Display tab. 
	  </description>
	</item>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 8.7.0 - A Chocolate and Vanilla Swirl</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-8.7.0-a-chocolate-and-vanilla-swirl.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-8.7.0-a-chocolate-and-vanilla-swirl.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2022 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  Mix a dark appearance in Notenik with a light System appearance; use Notenik as a project launcher, leveraging the versatility of Notenik&apos;s Link field; and further refine the appearance of a Web Book. It&apos;s all here in the latest release. 
	  </description>
	</item>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 8.6.0 - Checklists and Improved Title-as-Heading Options</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-8.6.0-checklists-and-improved-title-as-heading-options.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-8.6.0-checklists-and-improved-title-as-heading-options.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2022 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  Markdown Checklists are now available, as are more flexible options for formatting Note Titles, along with improved default CSS styling for headings, plus a new toggle for auto-creation of missing wiki link targets. 
	  </description>
	</item>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 8.5.0 - Support for YAML Metadata and Local Images</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-8.5.0-support-for-yaml-metadata-and-local-images.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-8.5.0-support-for-yaml-metadata-and-local-images.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Sun, 20 Feb 2022 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  YAML metadata is now a thing, and Notenik now supports it, in addition to its own special format. And then there&apos;s the problem of how to load local images into a Note, which now has a solution, allowing them to show up in the Display tab for the Note within Notenik. 
	  </description>
	</item>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 8.3.0 - A Few Hot Tips for Users Old and New</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-8.3.0-a-few-hot-tips-for-users-old-and-new.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-8.3.0-a-few-hot-tips-for-users-old-and-new.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Fri, 11 Feb 2022 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  Our first Notenik video, a new collection of brief Notenik Tips, the ability to jump to a random note in a collection, recall of Collection window sizes and positions, and a few more MathJax fixes &#8211; it&apos;s all part of the lastest Notenik release! 
	  </description>
	</item>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 8.2.0 - Setting the Table for New Users</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-8.2.0-setting-the-table-for-new-users.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-8.2.0-setting-the-table-for-new-users.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jan 2022 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  Added Markdown support for the creation of tables, using pipes and dashes; added a new command beneath the File menu to Open the current Collection&apos;s Folder in the macOS FInder; improved editing of Index fields; added new command to Clean a Link, removing common tracking parameters; improved the readability of the Keyboard Shortcuts Reference page in the Knowledge Base; added a new Markdown Cheat Sheet. 
	  </description>
	</item>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 8.0.0 - Including Several Neat Enhancements</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-8.0.0-including-several-neat-enhancements.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-8.0.0-including-several-neat-enhancements.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jan 2022 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  Added new Include command within the Notenik Markdown parser, to include a file, or another Note; expanded the Author Name Variable Modifierer to allow first name first to be extracted; added a new command and keyboard shortcut to quickly toggle the Streamlined Reading mode; added a new command to format a special Notenik URL to open the current Collection at a later date; added a new Merge Template Variable Modifier to perform a very rudimentary conversion of HTML to Markdown. 
	  </description>
	</item>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 7.9.0 - Taking Outlining to a New Level</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.9.0-taking-outlining-to-a-new-level.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.9.0-taking-outlining-to-a-new-level.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  This release includes a powerful new function for renumbering the Seq values for a range of Notes, indent and outdent commands, and some improvements to Web Book publishing. With these new options, outlining in Notenik is more powerful than ever. 
	  </description>
	</item>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 7.8.0 - Improvements to Streamlined Reading and Web Books</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.8.0-improvements-to-streamlined-reading-and-web-books.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.8.0-improvements-to-streamlined-reading-and-web-books.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2021 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  This release includes a new Notenik Intro, the addition of a new, optional header line when publishing a Web Book, a new <code>Include Children</code> field useful when using outlining with streamlined reading, and a new Sort option to view things in pure Date order (irrespective of Status). 
	  </description>
	</item>
  </channel>
</rss>
