<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
	<title>Notenik News</title>
	<link>https://notenik.app</link>
	<description>What's New with the Notenik app?</description>
	<language>en</language>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 7.9.0 - Taking Outlining to a New Level</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.9.0-taking-outlining-to-a-new-level.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.9.0-taking-outlining-to-a-new-level.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  This release includes a powerful new function for renumbering the Seq values for a range of Notes, indent and outdent commands, and some improvements to Web Book publishing. With these new options, outlining in Notenik is more powerful than ever. 
	  </description>
	</item>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 7.8.0 - Improvements to Streamlined Reading and Web Books</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.8.0-improvements-to-streamlined-reading-and-web-books.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.8.0-improvements-to-streamlined-reading-and-web-books.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2021 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  This release includes a new Notenik Intro, the addition of a new, optional header line when publishing a Web Book, a new <code>Include Children</code> field useful when using outlining with streamlined reading, and a new Sort option to view things in pure Date order (irrespective of Status). 
	  </description>
	</item>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 7.7.0 - Class Templates are Introduced</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.7.0-class-templates-are-introduced.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.7.0-class-templates-are-introduced.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Tue, 30 Nov 2021 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  This release introduces Class templates. Each different Class value within a Collection can have its own template, and that template can limit the fields included on the Edit tab for Notes of that Class, and can also supply default values for any fields that are included. This is one of those features that can be used in lots of different ways, for many different purposes, so it&apos;s worth sitting down and having a good think about how you might be able to put this feature to use for your Notes. 
	  </description>
	</item>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 7.6.0 - A Little Something for Everyone</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.6.0-a-little-something-for-everyone.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.6.0-a-little-something-for-everyone.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Tue, 09 Nov 2021 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  Notenik 7.6.0 should contain a little something for everyone, including some additional sort options, an improvement to the Quick Action window, more reasonable handling of data from deleted fields, the ability to include images in a Web Book, as well as the ability to specify your own available values for the new Class field. 
	  </description>
	</item>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 7.5.0 - A Few Small Improvements</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.5.0-a-few-small-improvements.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.5.0-a-few-small-improvements.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Thu, 28 Oct 2021 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  Notenik 7.5.0 makes a few small improvements, including reorganizing some of the app&apos;s menus, as well as rearranging things on the Collection Prefs screen. The Advanced Search option is the new feature that might be most widely appreciated. 
	  </description>
	</item>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 7.4.0 - Wiki Link Enhancements</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.4.0-wiki-link-enhancements.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.4.0-wiki-link-enhancements.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Thu, 14 Oct 2021 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  Notenik 7.4.0 addresses some common issues that often arise when making use of  Wiki Style Links. Welcome to backlinks, automatic target note creation, and AKA entries for your Notes! 
	  </description>
	</item>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 7.3.0 - A Handful of Helpful Refinements</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.3.0-a-handful-of-helpful-refinements.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.3.0-a-handful-of-helpful-refinements.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Thu, 30 Sep 2021 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  Version 7.3.0 of Notenik includes a handful of nifty changes: Improved Seq and Level Defaults for Drag and Drop; Improved Recognition of Parent Realm Folders; Parent Realm Folders Now Appear on Open Recent Menu; Streamlined New Collection process; Saving Security-Scoped Bookmarks; and Undo Provided for Note Deletions. 
	  </description>
	</item>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 7.2.0 - Some Nifty Enhancements</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.2.0-some-nifty-enhancements.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.2.0-some-nifty-enhancements.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Mon, 20 Sep 2021 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  Version 7.2.0 of Notenik includes a handful of nifty changes: the website address has been updated to point to Notenik.app; wiki links now will try to pluralize a reference, if it is not found in singular form; the Merge template Set command now allows a variable to be used as part or all of a global variable name; Markdown quote sharing corrected to respect lookup links; added a Quick Export and Open command. 
	  </description>
	</item>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 7.1.0 - Taking Dark Mode All the Way</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.1.0-taking-dark-mode-all-the-way.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.1.0-taking-dark-mode-all-the-way.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Tue, 31 Aug 2021 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  Notenik has mostly supported Dark Mode from the beginning &#8211; everywhere except on the Display tab, where the default was still to show black text on a white background. Now the Display Tab will follow your light/dark preferences, along with the rest of the App. 
	  </description>
	</item>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 7.0.0 - The Introduction of Lookup Fields</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.0.0-the-introduction-of-lookup-fields.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.0.0-the-introduction-of-lookup-fields.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Fri, 27 Aug 2021 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  A field in one Collection can now reference information in other Collections. 
	  </description>
	</item>
  </channel>
</rss>
