<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
	<title>Notenik News</title>
	<link>https://notenik.app</link>
	<description>What's New with the Notenik app?</description>
	<language>en</language>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 10.3.0 - More Bells, More Whistles</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-10.3.0-more-bells-more-whistles.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-10.3.0-more-bells-more-whistles.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Sat, 10 Sep 2022 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  Parent Realms gain new powers; improved file handling; improvements to Merge Template commands, variables and modifiers; plus a handful of fixes and tweaks. 
	  </description>
	</item>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik Turns 10.0.0!</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-turns-10.0.0.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-turns-10.0.0.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jul 2022 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  Well, the version-ometer has clicked over once again &#8211; as it tends to do every week or so with Notenik &#8211; and look where we&apos;ve landed: on the big 10.0.0! All those zeros seem to call for some sort of reflection on how we got here, so let&apos;s consider a few highlights. 
	  </description>
	</item>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 9.6.0 - Choose Your Edit Fonts</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-9.6.0-choose-your-edit-fonts.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-9.6.0-choose-your-edit-fonts.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jun 2022 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  You can now choose your own font(s) used on the Edit tab, and can also set default values for any of the fields in your Collection. 
	  </description>
	</item>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 9.5.0 Plus a Discourse Community</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-9.5.0-plus-a-discourse-community.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-9.5.0-plus-a-discourse-community.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2022 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  The big announcement this time is about the launch of a new Notenik community at discourse.notenik.app. But there&apos;s also info on an important bug fix and a few nice enhancements. 
	  </description>
	</item>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 9.3.0 - Cool New Functions</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-9.3.0-cool-new-functions.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-9.3.0-cool-new-functions.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2022 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  Expanded Note Selector to allow selection from other Collections; added an import option for a folder full of text files; modified the defaults for a new Level field to avoid values of zero; added a command to populate an app catalog; improved editing of the Status field. 
	  </description>
	</item>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 9.2.0 - Easy Commonplace Book with Lookup Fields</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-9.2.0-easy-commonplace-book-with-lookup-fields.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-9.2.0-easy-commonplace-book-with-lookup-fields.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2022 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  Added a new model Collection &#8211; a Commonplace Book using Lookup fields &#8211; that can be used to initialize a new Collection; added automatic generation of initial backlinks when adding a Backlinks field; straightened out some issues that could affect capture of metadata when importing/pasting a new Note into a Collection; fixed some problems associated with moving/copying a Collection, including initial population of a new Collection.  <br />

	  </description>
	</item>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 9.1.0 - Filling Some Holes</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-9.1.0-filling-some-holes.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-9.1.0-filling-some-holes.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2022 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  Added import option for a single text file (or simply drag and drop from the Finder); modified Discard of Edits to use a less common keyboard shortcut (Shift-CMD-D) and to provide a confirmation alert before proceeding; added a new Markdown command to produce a simple Tags Cloud; and added an option to remove all previously assigned tags based on level. 
	  </description>
	</item>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 9.0.1 - Hooked on Notenik</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-9.0.1-hooked-on-notenik.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-9.0.1-hooked-on-notenik.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Thu, 31 Mar 2022 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  The last couple of releases focused on better integration with other apps, including new Custom URL commands, new custom AppleScript commands, and the ability to integrate with the Hook app via their official scripts.  <br />

	  </description>
	</item>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 8.8.0 - Improvements to Note Editing</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-8.8.0-improvements-to-note-editing.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-8.8.0-improvements-to-note-editing.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Fri, 18 Mar 2022 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  Added a Note Selector window that allows a user, while remaining on Display or Edit of one Note, to look up the title of a second Note, for possible insertion into the text of the first Note; also expanded the width of the Body text editing field, and made inclusion of a &apos;Body:&apos; field label optional, on the Edit tab as well as the Display tab. 
	  </description>
	</item>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 8.7.0 - A Chocolate and Vanilla Swirl</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-8.7.0-a-chocolate-and-vanilla-swirl.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-8.7.0-a-chocolate-and-vanilla-swirl.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2022 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  Mix a dark appearance in Notenik with a light System appearance; use Notenik as a project launcher, leveraging the versatility of Notenik&apos;s Link field; and further refine the appearance of a Web Book. It&apos;s all here in the latest release. 
	  </description>
	</item>
  </channel>
</rss>
