<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
	<title>Notenik News</title>
	<link>https://notenik.app</link>
	<description>What's New with the Notenik app?</description>
	<language>en</language>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 8.3.0 - A Few Hot Tips for Users Old and New</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-8.3.0-a-few-hot-tips-for-users-old-and-new.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-8.3.0-a-few-hot-tips-for-users-old-and-new.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Fri, 11 Feb 2022 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  Our first Notenik video, a new collection of brief Notenik Tips, the ability to jump to a random note in a collection, recall of Collection window sizes and positions, and a few more MathJax fixes &#8211; it&apos;s all part of the lastest Notenik release! 
	  </description>
	</item>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 8.2.0 - Setting the Table for New Users</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-8.2.0-setting-the-table-for-new-users.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-8.2.0-setting-the-table-for-new-users.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jan 2022 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  Added Markdown support for the creation of tables, using pipes and dashes; added a new command beneath the File menu to Open the current Collection&apos;s Folder in the macOS FInder; improved editing of Index fields; added new command to Clean a Link, removing common tracking parameters; improved the readability of the Keyboard Shortcuts Reference page in the Knowledge Base; added a new Markdown Cheat Sheet. 
	  </description>
	</item>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 8.0.0 - Including Several Neat Enhancements</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-8.0.0-including-several-neat-enhancements.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-8.0.0-including-several-neat-enhancements.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jan 2022 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  Added new Include command within the Notenik Markdown parser, to include a file, or another Note; expanded the Author Name Variable Modifierer to allow first name first to be extracted; added a new command and keyboard shortcut to quickly toggle the Streamlined Reading mode; added a new command to format a special Notenik URL to open the current Collection at a later date; added a new Merge Template Variable Modifier to perform a very rudimentary conversion of HTML to Markdown. 
	  </description>
	</item>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 7.9.0 - Taking Outlining to a New Level</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.9.0-taking-outlining-to-a-new-level.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.9.0-taking-outlining-to-a-new-level.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  This release includes a powerful new function for renumbering the Seq values for a range of Notes, indent and outdent commands, and some improvements to Web Book publishing. With these new options, outlining in Notenik is more powerful than ever. 
	  </description>
	</item>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 7.8.0 - Improvements to Streamlined Reading and Web Books</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.8.0-improvements-to-streamlined-reading-and-web-books.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.8.0-improvements-to-streamlined-reading-and-web-books.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2021 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  This release includes a new Notenik Intro, the addition of a new, optional header line when publishing a Web Book, a new <code>Include Children</code> field useful when using outlining with streamlined reading, and a new Sort option to view things in pure Date order (irrespective of Status). 
	  </description>
	</item>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 7.7.0 - Class Templates are Introduced</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.7.0-class-templates-are-introduced.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.7.0-class-templates-are-introduced.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Tue, 30 Nov 2021 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  This release introduces Class templates. Each different Class value within a Collection can have its own template, and that template can limit the fields included on the Edit tab for Notes of that Class, and can also supply default values for any fields that are included. This is one of those features that can be used in lots of different ways, for many different purposes, so it&apos;s worth sitting down and having a good think about how you might be able to put this feature to use for your Notes. 
	  </description>
	</item>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 7.6.0 - A Little Something for Everyone</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.6.0-a-little-something-for-everyone.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.6.0-a-little-something-for-everyone.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Tue, 09 Nov 2021 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  Notenik 7.6.0 should contain a little something for everyone, including some additional sort options, an improvement to the Quick Action window, more reasonable handling of data from deleted fields, the ability to include images in a Web Book, as well as the ability to specify your own available values for the new Class field. 
	  </description>
	</item>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 7.5.0 - A Few Small Improvements</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.5.0-a-few-small-improvements.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.5.0-a-few-small-improvements.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Thu, 28 Oct 2021 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  Notenik 7.5.0 makes a few small improvements, including reorganizing some of the app&apos;s menus, as well as rearranging things on the Collection Prefs screen. The Advanced Search option is the new feature that might be most widely appreciated. 
	  </description>
	</item>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 7.4.0 - Wiki Link Enhancements</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.4.0-wiki-link-enhancements.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.4.0-wiki-link-enhancements.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Thu, 14 Oct 2021 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  Notenik 7.4.0 addresses some common issues that often arise when making use of  Wiki Style Links. Welcome to backlinks, automatic target note creation, and AKA entries for your Notes! 
	  </description>
	</item>
	<item>
	  <title>Notenik 7.3.0 - A Handful of Helpful Refinements</title>
	  <link>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.3.0-a-handful-of-helpful-refinements.html</link>
	  <guid>https://notenik.app/news/notenik-7.3.0-a-handful-of-helpful-refinements.html</guid>
	  <pubDate>Thu, 30 Sep 2021 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
	  <description>
		  Version 7.3.0 of Notenik includes a handful of nifty changes: Improved Seq and Level Defaults for Drag and Drop; Improved Recognition of Parent Realm Folders; Parent Realm Folders Now Appear on Open Recent Menu; Streamlined New Collection process; Saving Security-Scoped Bookmarks; and Undo Provided for Note Deletions. 
	  </description>
	</item>
  </channel>
</rss>
